An effective director will of course be alert
and inquisitive, will ask tough questions without being
disrespectful to others such that they don't put
management in a defensive position.
Directors should always be reminded that alongside management
they are supposed to be facing the same
direction and being careful not to put the
executives on the defensive, can challenge and should
challenge management assumptions without necessarily again putting them
on the defensive.
Another key element of board effectiveness is the
board agenda.
What is on the board agenda or what
should be on the board agenda?
One of the ways to streamline the board
agenda is to ensure that there's a delegation
of authority document that defines what matters come
to the board for approval, those are matters
that should feature on the board's agenda.
Matters that have been delegated to management shouldn't
feature on the board agenda but can come
to the board by way of reporting and
matters that are totally at the remit of
management and should only come to the board,
shouldn't even come to the board at all
either by way of information or otherwise.
So this helps to streamline the board's agenda
but typically matters that should be on the
board agenda relate to accountability, these essentially are
things that have happened in the past.
So we're reporting from quarter to quarter, we're
reporting for instance on the accounts, on for
instance performance over the quarter, yes that should
feature in the director's report to the board.
Matters of control, risk management, internal control and
all of those are again issues that have
happened in the past.
More future focused matters where the board should
spend most of its time are around strategy,
around the culture of the organisation, foresight, things
around foresight, those are things that many boards
don't spend too much time on but those
are things that can actually impact the quality
of board decisions and the quality of board
deliberations.
So whilst it might be difficult for the
board to look at each of these items
at a typical board meeting, the board plan
for the year should feature all of these
items that have been discussed.
Another element of board effectiveness is the board's
ability to identify and deal with dysfunctional directors.
What are some of the qualities of dysfunctionality?
A director that is often absent at board
meetings, is always unprepared for meetings, they don't
read their board papers, they don't do any
research ahead of such meetings, never willing to
offer a dissenting view, they agree with everything
that is said and never declares a conflict
of interest.
So you have a director who is consistently
interested in matters on the agenda but never
discloses such interests, that person is dysfunctional and
disruptive, has an overbearing or domineering style, they
always want to have the last word and
clearly such position always suppresses dissent or diversity
of opinion.